

#### **CONTACT**

- ARIES Observatory
  Nainital-263001
  Uttarkhand, India
- +91 5942-270-704
- bibhuti@aries.res.in
- https://bibhuraushan.github.io

#### RESEARCH SKILLS

#### • Image Processing

Image restoration, feature identification, feature tracking and other processing in the historical and modern space based solar images.

#### • Numerical Techniques

Roots finding, differentiation, integration, solution of multidimensional linear equations, solution of differential equations, etc.

#### Data Statistics

Descriptive and Inferential statistics (Frequentist and Bayesian Inferences), etc.

#### Machine Learning

Linear Regression, classification (K-means clustering), Feature identification based on ML & Al (beginner)

## **BIBHUTI KUMAR JHA**

Post Doctoral Researcher IIA, Bangalore & ARIES, Nainital

#### AREA OF RESEARCH

My primary area of research is Solar Astrophysics. I work on century-long archived data obtained at the different ground and space-based observatories to understand the long-term variation in the Sun. I work on the development of automatic algorithms using various image processing and mathematical techniques to extract solar magnetic features from digital images. Then, I study and analyse the physical parameters extracted from these features to understand the physics underneath. In addition, I am also interested in the Solar Dynamo theory to understand the magnetic cycle of the Sun.

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

- Post Doctoral Researcher (PDR) Indian Institute of Astrophysics (IIA), Bangalore & Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences (ARIES), Nainital; (Feb 2022 on-wards)
- Senior Research Fellow (SRF) Indian Institute of Astrophysics (IIA), Bangalore & Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences (ARIES), Nainital; (Jan 2019 – Jan 2022)
- Junior Research Fellow (JRF) Indian Institute of Astrophysics (IIA), Bangalore (Jan 2017 – Jan 2019)

#### **EDUCATION**

• **Ph.D. (Solar Astrophysics):** Indian Institute of Astrophysics (IIA), Bangalore & Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences (ARIES), Nainital; **(2017–2022)** 

Thesis Title: Long-term study of the Sun and its implications to solar dynamo models

Thesis Supervisor: Prof. Dipankar Banerjee

(Thesis Submitted on 3rd February, 2022 to Pondicherry University, India)

- M.Sc. (Physics): Department of Physics & Astrophysics, University of Delhi, New Delhi, India; (2014–2016)
- B.Sc. (Physics): Dyal Singh College, University of Delhi, New Delhi, India: (2011–2014)

## **PUBLICATIONS**

 A theoretical model of the near-surface shear layer of the Sun Bibhuti Kumar Jha & Arnab Rai Choudhuri; MNRAS (2021) 506:2 (2189)

# COMPUTER SKILLS

C, C++	9+ yrs
IDL, Python	5+ yrs
Mathematica	1+ yrs
R, Rust, Julia	2+ yrs
LaTex, Html/CSS	5+ yrs
Adobe Photoshop	8+ yrs
Adobe Lightroom	3+ yrs
InkScape	2+ yrs

## **PROFILES**

- NASA ADS
- Google Scholar
- ArXive
- % ORCID
- ResearchGate



 Measurements of Solar Differential Rotation Using the Century Long Kodaikanal Sunspot Data

Bibhuti Kumar Jha, Aditya Priyadarshi, Sudip Mandal, Subhamoy Chatterjee & Dipankar Banerjee; *Sol Phys (2021) 296: 25* 

 Magnetic field dependence of bipolar magnetic region tilts on the Sun: Indication of tilt quenching

Bibhuti Kumar Jha, Bidya Binay Karak, Sudip Mandal, Dipankar Banerjee; *APjL (2020) 889:L19* 

Delving into the Historical Ca II K Archive from the Kodaikanal Observatory: the Potential of the Most Recent Digitised Series

Theodosios Chatzistergos, Ilaria Ermolli, Sami K. Solanki, Natalie A. Krivova, Dipankar Banerjee, Bibhuti K. Jha, Subhamoy Chatterjee; *Sol Phys (2019)* 294: 145

 Study of Sunspot Penumbra to Umbra Area Ratio Using Kodaikanal Whitelight Digitised Data

Bibhuti Kumar Jha, Sudip Mandal, & Dipankar Banerjee, *Sol Phys (2019)* 294: 72

 Long-term variation of sunspot penumbra to umbra ratio: A study using Kodaikanal white-light digitized data

Bibhuti Kumar Jha, Sudip Mandal, & Dipankar Banerjee 2018, *Proceedings of the International Astronomical*, *Union*, 13, 185–186

#### **CONFERENCES AND MEETINGS**

- Presented a talk titled A Theoretical Model of the Near-Surface Shear Layer of the Sun, The 15th Quadrennial Solar-Terrestrial Physics (STP-15) symposium, 21-25 February, 2022, Online
- Presented a e-poster titled A Theoretical Model of the Near-Surface Shear Layer of the Sun, The 16th European Solar Physics Meetings (ESPM-16), 6-10 September, 2021, Online
- Presented a talk titled Signature of quenching from observation of tilted bipolar magnetic regions on the Sun, IIA-50 Conference - Advances in Observations and Modelling of Solar Magnetism and Variability, 1-4 March, 2021, IIA, Bangalore, India
- Presented a talk titled Magnetic field dependence of bipolar magnetic region tilts on the Sun: Evidence of tilt quenching, Astronomical Society of India Meeting 2020, 13-17 February, 2020, IISER Tirupati, India
- Presented a poster titled Solar differential rotation as measured from century long Kodaikanal white light digitized data, 5th Asia Pacific Solar Physics Meeting (APSPM), 3-7 February, IUCAA, Pune, India
- Presented a poster titled Magnetic field dependency of bipolar magnetic region tilt angle: A study using MDI and HMI data sets, IRIS-10, 4-8 November, 2019, Christ University Bangalore, India
- Presented a poster titled Solar Differential Rotation in last century: A study from Kodaikanal white light digitised data, Young Astronomers Meet, 23-27 September, 2019, Kodaikanal Solar Observatory, IIA Kodaikanal, India
- Attended Solar Physics Summer School at Raman Science Center,10 -16 June, 2019, Leh, India
- Presented an oral talk titled An update on Kodaikanal Digital Archived
   Data in a meeting entitled "Reconstructing Solar and Heliospheric Magnetic Field Evolution Over the Past Century", ISSI Team led by Alexei Pevtsov; 12 15 February, 2019
- Presented an oral talk titled Magnetic field dependency of Bipolar magnetic region tilt angle: A study from SOHO/MDI data, Young Astronomers Meet, 24-28 September, 2018, PRL, Ahmadabad, India

## **OTHER SKILLS**

#### **Photography**

Apart from my research work photography is the area where I spend most of my time.

- Attended Heliophysics Summer School, 23 20 July, 2018 Boulder, Colorado, USA
- Presented a poster titled Long-term variation of sunspot penumbra to umbra ratio: A study using Kodaikanal white-light digitized data., IAUS-340, 19 - 24 February, 2018, Jaipur, India

## **VISITS**

- Visiting Scholar at Indian Institute of Technology (IIT), Banaras Hindu University (BHU), Varanasi, India; December 2018
- Visiting Scholar at Max Planck Institute for Solar System Research, Göttingen, Germany; Feb May, 2019

## **FELLOWSHIPS**

· CSIR NET-JRF 2017